Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Adela Akers papers
1960-2009
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Akers, Adela
2.6 linear feet
The papers of fiber artist and educator Adela Akers measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1960 to 2009. Her career as an artist and her tenure at the Tyler School of Art, Temple University, are documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence; subject files on galleries, projects, weaving technique, research, workshops, and fiber arts organizations; writings; exhibition announcements, clippings, and other printed material; photographs; and artwork, including one sketchbook.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 2009 and 2011 by Adela Akers.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Adela Akers, 2008 Mar. 4-6, conducted by Mija Riedel.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Adela Akers (1933- ) is a fiber artist and educator living and working in Guerneville, California.
Akers was born in Santiago de Compostela, Spain, and was raised in Havana, Cuba. She came to the United States as a student in 1957 and studied at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago and Cranbrook Academy of Art. In 1965 she served as a weaving advisor in Peru for the Alliance for Progress and was an artist in residence at Penland School of Crafts from 1968-1970. From 1972 to 1995 Akers was a professor and chair of fiber arts at the Tyler School of Art at Temple University in Philadelphia. Her weavings consist of zigzags, checkerboard patterns, and simple geometric shapes.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of fiber artist and educator Adela Akers measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1960 to 2009. Her career as an artist and her tenure at the Tyler School of Art, Temple University, are documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence; subject files on galleries, projects, weaving technique, research, workshops, and fiber arts organizations; writings; exhibition announcements, clippings, and other printed material; photographs; and artwork, including one sketchbook.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1970s, 1991-1998 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1960-2007 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1973-1995 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1962-2009 (Box 1-2, 6; 6 folders)
Series 6: Photographic Materials, 1960-2008 (Box 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 3-6, OV 7; 1.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Fiber artists--California; Educators--California; Weaving--Technique
Types of Materials:
Sketchbooks; Photographs
Names:
Tyler School of Art
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1970s, 1991-1998, Series 1:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Found here are scattered employment records from Akers's tenure in the Craft Department at Tyler School of Art, one award certificate, and several draft versions of her resume.
  - Employment Records, Tyler School of Art, 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resume, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Temple University Faculty Award for Creative Achievement, 1995, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1985-1987, Series 2:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Correspondence documents Akers's professional dealings with art galleries, museums, organizations, and services, from 1985-1987. Researchers should note that additional correspondence is included in Series 3: Subject Files.
  Correspondence is arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1985-1987, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Subject Files, 1960-2007, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  Found here are subject files which Akers maintained to document her work with galleries and fiber arts organizations, exhibitions, lectures and workshops, and commissioned projects. Also found are files on weaving technique and research on other fiber artists. Files may include correspondence, notes, printed material, agreements, lists of artwork, and a few scattered photographs.
  Files are arranged alphabetically. Akers's original folder titles were maintained.
  - Adelle M. Fine Arts, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Advanced Weaving, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Craft Museum, 1985-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Art Exchange, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Arts Benicia, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Columbus Cultural Arts Center, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Connecticut Commission on the Arts, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Crieger Associaties, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Double Weave, 1960-1970s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Felting, circa 1970s-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fiberworks, Center for the Textile Arts, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fiberworks Symposium, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Galman Lepow Associates, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Guatemala, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Helen Drutt Gallery, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lectures and Workshops, 1967-1971, circa 1979, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Library Tapestry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lonny Gans and Associates, 1982-1990, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - NEA International Fellowships, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Netting, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Patrick King Contemporary Art, 1981-1991, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Plaiting, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Study Leave Research, Neda Al-Hilali, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Study Leave Research, Francoise Grossen, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Study Leave Research, Cynthia Schira, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Study Leave Research, Joanne Segal Brandford, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Temple University Research Grants, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Thirteen Moons Gallery, 2002-2007, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Tyler School of Art Grant Reports, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - University Hospital of Cleveland, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Weaving Techniques, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Writings, 1973-1995, Series 4:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Writings consist of loose notes on weaving and one weaving notebook. Both contain notes, diagrams, illustrations, and lists. The weaving notebook also includes attached fiber samples.
  The weaving notebook was removed from a three-ring binder and the original order of the pages has been maintained.
  - Notes, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Weaving Notebook, 1985-1995, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
- Printed Material, 1962-2009, Series 5:; (Box 1-2, 6; 6 folders)
  Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements, news clippings and magazines containing mentions of Akers, and one publication regarding Akers's work for the Alliance for Progress program in Peru.
  - Catalogs, 1968, 1994-2006 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1986-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, 1966-2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1962-1995, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - "Adela Akers and the Weavers of Huhi," 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Photographic Materials, 1960-2008, Series 6:; (Box 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
  Photographs depict Adela Akers working in her studio, an exhibition installation and opening at Shop One Gallery, artworks in progresss, and weavings by Akers. Also found are digital photographs, negatives, transparencies, and slides of her artwork.
  - Photographs of Adela Akers, 1960-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Home and Studio, 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Shop One Gallery, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Works in Progress, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1967-1990, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Digital Photographs of Artwork, 2004-2007, (six data disks) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Negatives and Transparencies, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Slides, 1970s-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Artwork, circa 1960s-1980s, Series 7:; (Box 3-6, OV 7; 1.1 linear feet)
  Artwork by Akers consists of one bound sketchbook, three three-dimensional studies, and 32 color studies for her weavings.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Proposal #1," circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Proposal #2," circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Proposal #1," circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Color Studies, circa 1980s (Box OV 7)